Finding Aid for Programs for Educational Opportunity (University of Michigan) publications, 1973-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Programs for Educational Opportunity (University of Michigan) publications
1973-1996
University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunity.
9778 Bimu 2
A race desegregation assistance center based at the University of Michigan, the Program for Educational Opportunity was established by funding through the 1964 Civil Rights Act. The program was expanded to encompass race, gender, and national origin equity in public schools in the Great Lakes region. Includes reports, brochures, pamphlets and other material relating to racial segregation and racial and sex discrimination in education.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor # ).
The publications are open for research.
See history found in the manuscript finding aid for PER records
The Publications series of the Programs for Educational Opportunity measures 3 linear feet and covers the period from 1973 to the present. This series is divided into two subseries: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunity.; School discipline--Michigan.; Minorities--Education--Michigan.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Detroit.; Public schools--Michigan.; Educational counseling--Michigan.; Discrimination in education--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in education--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; Multicultural education--Michigan.; School integration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Education--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Center for Sex Equity in Schools.; University of Michigan. Project for the Fair Administration of Student Discipline.; University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunity.
Genre Terms:
Pamphlets.; Bibliographies.; Brochures.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.
- Publications
  - Unit Publications
    Unit Publications include anthologies, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins, calendars, directories, manuals, proceedings, and reports. The bibliographies list sources focusing on the diversity of American society such as Books about Chicano Children or Selected Bibliography for Use in Discovering Native American Culture Through Art. The calendars feature photographs taken in local Ann Arbor public schools and commemorate dates important to many diverse cultures. Under "manuals" researchers will find editions of the publication Tune in to Your Rights...A Guide for Teenagers About Turning Off Sexual Harassment in Arabic, English, and Spanish. The other publications found under this heading include lesson plans and guides for instruction of a multicultural curriculum.
    The bulletin Breakthrough was published from 1972 through 1988. Title IX Line was published from 1975 to 1978 by Programs for Educational Opportunity. There were twelve issues of this publication. From 1981 to 1986 another bulletin under the same title was published by the Center for Sex Equity in Schools, which is a sub-unit of Programs for Educational Opportunity. That bulletin will be found in Sub-Units under the name of the publishing office. The Bentley Library holds volumes 2-7. The Equity Coalition for Race, Gender, and National Origin was first published in 1989 and continues publication. The Bentley Library holds a complete run of this publication.
    Programs for Educational Opportunity sponsored several conferences which discussed various aspects of education including segregation and desegregation, equal opportunity, student behavior and discipline, and multicultural education. The proceedings of these conferences, most of which were held in the 1970s, will be found under the heading "Proceedings". Reports covering the same topics will be found under the heading "Reports".
    - Anthologies
      - Affirmative Action, undated (Box 1)
    - Anthologies
      - Readings in Equalizing Educational Opportunity and School Desegregation, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles about PER
      - Educational Opportunities: What Are They? Where Are They? Who Finds Them?, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies
      - Bibliography for a Yearbook of Holidays and Observances: A Multicultural Perspective, 1991 (Box 1)
      - Bibliography of Multi-cultural Materials Collected for Display at the Conference on Diversity in Educational Opportunity, 1974 (Box 1)
      - Books About Chicano Children, undated (Box 1)
      - Chicano Bibliography, undated (Box 1)
      - Education and the Law Bibliography, 1974 (Box 1)
      - Hispanic Americans in the United States: A Selected Bibliography, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Resource Center Monograph Holdings as of June 30, 1974, [1974] (Box 1)
      - Selected Bibliography for Use In Discovering Native American Culture Through Art, undated (Box 1)
      - Student Rights and Responsibilities: A Legal-Educational Bibliography, undated (Box 1)
      - Utilizing Evaluative Information to Diffuse Educational Innovations: An Annotated Bibliography, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Brochures
      - Conferences, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
      - Conferences, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
      - Leadership Workshops, 1994-2002 (Box 1)
      - Programs for Educational Opportunity, undated (Box 1)
      - We Can Help You Help the Children, undated (Box 1)
    - Bulletins
      - Breakthrough, vol. 1-15, 1972-1988; 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Equity Coalition for Race, Gender, and National Origin,, vol. 1-4, 1989-1996; 1999; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Program for Educational Opportunity, undated (Box 1)
      - Title IX Line, no. 1-12, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - Calendars
      - Multicultural Calendar
        - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
        - 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1992-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Multiethnic Calendar
        - 1982 (Box 1)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - A Yearbook of Holidays and Observances: A Multicultural Perspective of Celebrations in the United States, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Directories
      - Regional Equity Network Directory, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Manuals
      - Agarra La Onda de tus Derechos...Una Guia Para Jovenes de Como Combatir el Acoso Sexual, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Co-ed Physical Education Activities and Strategies, undated (Box 1)
      - Desegregation and Integration Planning Resource Book, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Diversity Awareness Workshop Manual (Michigan Metro Girl Scout Council), 1992 (Box 1)
      - From Jumpstart: A Story of Black Music; Secondary School Teaching Guide, 1980 (Box 1)
      - Handbook of Training Activities to Combat Sexism in Education, undated (Box 1)
      - Implementing Multicultural Curriculum: A Handbook, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Metron System Alias: The Metric System, undated (Box 1)
      - Multicultural
        - Experiences in Mathematics Using "Evan's Corner", 1974 (Box 1)
        - Exploring Multi-cultural Identities Through Art, undated (Box 1)
        - Multi-cultural Art Projects, [ca. 1975] (Box 1)
        - The Quest for Food, 1974 (Box 1)
        - A Response Through the Visual Arts to "Evan's Corner" [ca. 1975] (Box 1)
        - Soups' Cookin' in the Classroom, [1974] (Box 1)
      - Tune in to Your Rights...A Guide for Teenagers About Turning Off Sexual Harassment, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Tune in to Your Rights...A Guide for Teenagers About Turning Off Sexual Harassment (Arabic version), undated (Box 1)
      - What's It Worth? A Simulation for the Training of School Personnel in the Administration of Comparable Worth Studies, undated (Box 1)
      - Who's Hurt and Who's Liable: Sexual Harassment in Massachusetts Schools, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Proceedings
      - Alternative Education in a Pluralistic Society, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Approaches for Achieving a Multicultural Curriculum, undated (Box 2)
      - Bilingual-Bicultural Education, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Cross-Cultural Communication in the Schools, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Counseling for Equal Opportunity, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Curricular, Instructional and Supervisory Decision-Making to Meet Changing Educational Needs, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Desegregation and Beyond: The Educational and Legal Issues, undated (Box 2)
      - Developments in School Desegregation and the Law, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Diversity in Educational Opportunities, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Educational Policies and Equal Educational Opportunity, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Equal Educational Opportunity in High School Athletics, undated (Box 2)
      - Humanistic Education in Desegregated Schools, undated (Box 2)
      - Implementing Title IX in PE and Athletics, 1978 (Box 2)
      - A Look at the Education of Teachers: Preservice and In-Service, undated (Box 2)
      - Magnet School/Title IV Desegregation Programs: Proceedings of the 1993 Conference (Box 2)
      - Multicultural Education: Instruction and Curriculum, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Overcoming Segregation and Discrimination: Recent Legal and Educational Developments, 1977 (Box 2)
      - The Role of the School Social Worker in the Desegregation Process, 1974 (Box 2)
      - School Desegregation, Public Information and the Media, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Sex Equality and Title IX, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Student Behavior, Rights and Responsibilities and the Fair Administration of Discipline, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Student Rights and Discipline: Policies, Programs, and Procedures, 1978 (Box 3)
      - A Symposium on Special Student Concerns Projects, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - America's Hispanic Heritage, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Assessment of Selected Dimensions of the Discipline Process at Building Ten, District C, [1980] (Box 3)
      - Controlled Choice: A New and Effective Desegregation Method, 1995 (Box 3)
      - Critical Issues in the Education of Black Children, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Cultural Encounters: Some Truths About the Melting Pot, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Identifying and Utilizing Resources for School Desegregation, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Individualizing Instruction to Promote Equal Learning Opportunities in a Multicultural Setting, 1978 (Box 3)
      - An Intercultural Approach to a Multi-Cultural Education, undated (Box 3)
      - Nondiscriminatory Employment Decision-Making in Public Schools, undated (Box 3)
      - The Status of Desegregation in Michigan, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Student Rights, Responsibilities and Discipline, undated (Box 3)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    Sub-Unit Publications include publications from the Center for Sex Equity in Schools. The bibliography Women, Math and Science: A Resource Manual is a compilation of resources describing the problems and difficulties for young women studying math and science as well as solutions on how to encourage them into these disciplines. The Bentley Library holds the 1984, 1987, and 1996 editions of the manual Remember the Ladies: A Handbook of Women in American History. The center also published a manual entitled Susan B. Anthony Day Handbook which gives a short biography of Susan B. Anthony, primary source material relating to Susan B. Anthony, a bibliography of women's issues, and potential classroom activities to celebrate Susan B. Anthony Day. Women's History Week March 6-12 is a series of lesson plans focusing on women in American history.
    The Project for the Fair Administration of Student Discipline includes a bibliography entitled Student Rights and School Discipline published in 1975. Its update was issued in 1976. This sub-unit also published a report entitled Assessing Disproportionate Minority Suspensions: A High School Case Study published in 1980.
    - Center for Sex Equity in Schools (Box 3)
      - Bibliographies
        - Rainbows, 1982 (Box 3)
        - Women, Math and Science: A Resource Manual, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Brochures, undated (Box 3)
      - Manuals
        - Remember the Ladies: A Handbook of Women in American History
          - 1984 (Box 3)
          - 1987 (Box 3)
          - 1996 (Box 3)
        - Susan B. Anthony Day Handbook, 1979 (Box 3)
        - Women's History Week March 6-12, undated (Box 3)
      - Newsletters
        - Title IX Line,, vol. 2-7, 1981-1986; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Reports
        - Title IX Self Evaluation Guide for Elementary and Secondary School Districts, undated (Box 3)
    - Project for the Fair Administration of Student Discipline
      - Bibliographies
        - Student Rights and School Discipline: Bibliography, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Student Rights and School Discipline: Bibliography, Update No. 1, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Reports
        - Assessing Disproportionate Minority Suspensions: A High School Case Study, 1980 (Box 3)
        - Fair Discipline Project, Final Report, 1983 (Box 3)
        - Sex Equity Project-Detroit Public Schools, 1983 (Box 3)
Related Material
Programs in Educational Opportunity (University of Michigan) records 1969-2002.
School of Education (University of Michigan) records 1904-ongoing.